Robotics Interviews, 1989-1990
Smithsonian Institution Archives
Robotics Interviews
1989-1990
Smithsonian Institution Archives, Washington, D.C., osiaref@si.edu
Oral Histories
files (Reference copies).
Record Unit 9552
Historical Note
Robotics is the applied science of intelligent machines, a field of research that combines electrical, electronic, and mechanical engineering. Steven Lubar, curator in the Division of Engineering and Industry at the Smithsonian's National Museum of American History (NMAH), recorded four sessions with robots designers to document different work styles, environments, and the processes by which engineers make decisions. He captured the style of work at two university settings and a corporate site to understand how their differing objectives influenced technological development. His goal was to interview researchers working with their machines--to document the "hands-on" aspect of development--and to record the robots in use. Lubar was also interested in documenting the interactions between researchers, the robots, and their environment.
Introduction
The Smithsonian Videohistory Program, funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation from 1986 until 1992, used video in historical research. Additional collections have been added since the grant project ended. Videohistory uses the video camera as a historical research tool to record moving visual information. Video works best in historical research when recording people at work in environments, explaining artifacts, demonstrating process, or in group discussion. The experimental program recorded projects that reflected the Institution's concern with the conduct of contemporary science and technology.
Smithsonian historians participated in the program to document visual aspects of their on-going historical research. Projects covered topics in the physical and biological sciences as well as in technological design and manufacture. To capture site, process, and interaction most effectively, projects were taped in offices, factories, quarries, laboratories, observatories, and museums. Resulting footage was duplicated, transcribed, and deposited in the Smithsonian Institution Archives for scholarship, education, and exhibition. The collection is open to qualified researchers.
Descriptive Entry
Session participants included students, professors, technicians, and engineers. Session One took place in the Department of Mechanical Engineering at the University of Maryland, College Park, Maryland, on March 31, 1989. Lubar focused on the development of a robot at a university with a strong engineering tradition and a program with very practical goals. Lung-We Tsai, Jigien "Roger" Chen, and Shapour Azarm, professors in the department, oversaw the development and production of a robot designed by students for a national competition. The professors discussed the competition and the university's involvement with it, student participation and their level of effort, design of robots, and the nature of engineering design and its application to robots. This highly visual session also documented the students' work in the laboratory and machine shop, and classroom progress reports about the robot under construction.
Session Two took place at Odetics, Inc., in Anaheim, California, on December 14, 1989, where Lubar documented the only commercial firm currently producing walking robots. While there, he talked with Steve Bartholet, the inventor of the firm's first walking robot, ODEX I. Bartholet spoke about initial concepts and design configurations, and demonstrated structural features of the robot while it walked. Lubar also talked with Robert Drap, who designed the computer system for a self-contained machine. Joel Slutzkey, Odetics president, provided the overview of the company's role in robotics research and development. Finally, Lubar interviewed technicians involved in the most recent phase of robotics development, ODEX III. Armen Sivaslian determined production methods and demonstrated telescopic leg structure. Steven Corley, a software developer, demonstrated the debugging process (modify and re-code) for software that controlled the robot's leg operations.
Session Three took place at the Robotics Institute of Carnegie-Mellon University (CMU), Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on September 20 and 21, 1990. The Institute was established in 1979 to bring together cooperative programs between academia and industry to conduct research in robotics technologies relevant to industrial problems. The focus of the session was to record the history of Ambler (Autonomous Mobile Exploration Robot), a six-legged walking robot commissioned by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) to explore and sample the planetary surface of Mars. Lubar recorded a weekly integration meeting of production leaders and students involved with Ambler, a group interview with four Ambler project leaders, and a work session in the Ambler control room where students discussed and resolved some of the robot's movement problems.
Ambler project leaders interviewed included Erik Krotkov, professor and research scientist for the Ambler, Kevin Dowling, a graduate student who served previously as project manager for the Ambler before his current position as project manager for NASA Space Shuttle ground operations robot development, Henning Pangels, a graduate student leader of Ambler's physical control and real-time computing team, and John Bares, a Ph.D. candidate responsible for Ambler's configuration design. Participants in the control room included Pangels, and CMU students David Wettergreen and Regis Hoffman. Finally, Brian Albrecht, current Ambler project manager, conducted a visual tour of the Ambler robot.
Session Four provided an overview of the Robotics Institute's philosophy and research interests. Albrecht led Lubar on a laboratory tour highlighting other CMU-designed robots and discussed the history of their development. Lubar also interviewed William "Red" Whittaker, director and principal research scientist of the Field Robotics Center of the Robotics Institute since 1986. Finally, Lubar visited the Learning Robots Laboratory, a CMU lab devoted to developing robots that automatically improve their performance through experience. Peter S. Tanguy, CMU student, demonstrated movement of a robot arm and described task oriented vision.
The series includes two sets of supplemental tapes. Steven Lubar shot the first set of supplemental tape on July 24, 1989, at the National Bureau of Standards about its robot, "Erica." Thomas Wheatley and James Albus spoke about the robot, and offered demonstration. The second set was recorded on April 20-21, 1989, at Texas Technical University, where faculty member Jaime Cardenas-Garcia and crew videotaped the "Walking Machine Decathalon," in which the robot from the University of Maryland competed (and took second place). This supplemental sessions is comprised of four VHS tapes, which include "Rules," "Student Presentations," and "Preliminary Judging."
This collection consists of four interview sessions and two supplementary sessions, totalling approximately 12:20 hours of recordings (not including supplementary session 2), and 102 pages of transcript. There are three generations of tape for each session: originals, dubbing masters, and reference copies. In total, this collection is comprised of 37 originals (34 Beta videotapes, and 3 U-matic videotapes; not including supplementary session 2), 14 dubbing masters (14 U-matic videotapes; not including supplementary session 2), and 8 reference videotapes (8 VHS videotapes; not including Supplementary session 2). Supplementary session 2 is comprised of 8:00 hours of recordings on 4 reference copy (VHS) videotapes. The collection has been remastered digitally, with 37 motion jpeg 2000 and 37 mpeg digital files for preservation, and 14 Windows Media Video and 14 Real Media Video digital files for reference. Supplementary session 2 was not digitized.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following access terms. These are links to collections with related topics, persons or places.
Name
Tsai, Lung-We.; Chen, Jigien.; Azarm, Shapour.; Drap, Robert.; Slutzkey, Joel.; Sivaslian, Armen.; Corley, Steven.; Krotkov, Erik.; Dowling, Kevin.; Pangels, Henning.; Bares, John.; Wettergreen, David.; Hoffman, Regis.; Whittaker, William.; Tanguy, Peter S.; Albus, James.; Wheatley, Thomas.; Carnegie-Mellon University (Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania); Odetics Incorporated (Anaheim, California); University of Maryland at College Park
Subject
History of science and technology; Engineering; Robotics
Co-Creator
Tsai, Lung-We. interviewee.; Chen, Jigien. interviewee.; Azarm, Shapour. interviewee.; Drap, Robert. interviewee.; Slutzkey, Joel. interviewee.; Sivaslian, Armen. interviewee.; Corley, Steven. interviewee.; Krotkov, Erik. interviewee.; Dowling, Kevin. interviewee.; Pangels, Henning. interviewee.; Bares, John. interviewee.; Wettergreen, David. interviewee.; Hoffman, Regis. interviewee.; Whittaker, William. interviewee.; Tanguy, Peter S. interviewee.; Albus, James. interviewee.; Wheatley, Thomas. interviewee.; Lubar, Steven D. interviewer.
Physical Characteristics of Materials in the Collection
Interviews; Interviews; Videotapes; Oral history
- Box 1
  - Transcripts of Interviews
  - Session 1: 31 March 1989 (Box 1 of 1)
    In the shops and classrooms of the Department of Mechanical Engineering, University of Maryland, College Park, Maryland, featured Tsai, Chen, Azarm, and students discussing the design and development of robots at the university, c. 1986-1989, including:
    history of the walking robot competition
    students' role in the design and development process and level of involvement
    robot design changes and improvements
    troubleshooting in the laboratory, machine shop, and classroom.
    Visual documentation included:
    tours of student laboratory and machine shop
    milling and refinement process
    student interaction and problem solving
    demonstration of walking robot.
    Transcript 1-24 pages, of videotape recording, 2 hours, 20 minutes.
  - Session 2: 14 December 1989 (Box 1 of 1)
    In the meeting rooms and development areas, Odetics, Inc., Anaheim, California, featured Bartholet, Drapp, Slutzkey, Sivaslian, and Corley discussing the development of a robot at the corporate level, c. 1970-1989, including:
    Odetics, Inc., history and products
    ODEX I mechanical and structural design
    ODEX I electronic operating systems (IBM PC/model 1)
    ODEX I models
    possible markets and working applications for robot
    ODEX III mechanical and structural design
    ODEX III telescopic legs for nesting, spacing, tracking
    ODEX III placement of foot
    ODEX III algorithms and internal mechanisms
    performance of walking algorithms
    configuration for method of walking
    debugging communication software
    evaluation of mechanical and hardware development
    "on-ground" and "in-air" testing.
    ODEX I walking, "kneeling," following commands
    ODEX I close-ups of structural features
    ODEX III close-ups of telescopic legs
    ODEX III computer screen and command algorithms
    ODEX III demonstration of "in-air" and "on-ground" walking.
    Transcript, 1-78 pages, of videotape recording, 3 hours, 20 minutes.
  - Session 3: 20 September 1990 (Box 1 of 1)
    At the Field Robotics Center of the Robotics Institute, Carnegie-Mellon University, featured Krotkov, Dowling, Pangels, Bares, Wettergreen, Hoffman and Albrecht discussing various aspects of the development of the Ambler, c. 1985-1989, including:
    Ambler Integration Meeting focusing on the development and progress of the robot's foot
    history of Ambler's development
    influence of earlier CMU robots, especially Teregator, on design decisions for Ambler
    initial proposal and NASA's specification requirements
    development of Ambler's "single-stack" leg design and decision to change to the "double-stack" leg configuration
    application of perception to robotics
    development of laser rangefinders and terrain mapping
    team decision-making process and role of principal investigators
    description of Task Control Architecture
    future plans for Ambler
    Ambler's operations from the control room
    map building with the Perceptron Scanning Laser Rangefinder
    visual tour of the Ambler's components.
    discussion among students and team leaders at weekly Integration Meeting
    sketch for initial Ambler proposal to NASA
    photo of Teregator
    Ambler prototype models
    photo of Ambler single-leg test bed
    Task Control Architecture flow chart
    use of control room computers
    close-up of Perceptron image on video monitor
    computer generation of a terrain map
    close-ups of all components of Ambler
    demonstration of Ambler leg movement.
    Transcript, 1-78 pages, of videotape recording, 3 hours, 40 minutes.
  - Session 4: 21 September 1990 (Box 1 of 1)
    At the Field Robotics Center and Learning Robots Laboratory at Carnegie-Mellon University, featured Albrecht, Whittaker and Tanguy discussing various projects undertaken by The Robotics Institute, c. 1978-1989, including:
    tour of earlier Field Robotics Center robots
    history of development of autonomous vehicles
    Whittaker's background and establishment of the Field Robotics Center
    Carnegie-Mellon's philosophy of robotics
    use of Task Control Architecture
    future applications for robotics
    functions of the Learning Robots Laboratory
    description of task-oriented vision
    use of robot arms in industrial settings.
    Field Robotics Center laboratory
    interior and exterior of the NAVLAB autonomous vehicle
    Locomotion Emulator wheeled robot
    various laser rangefinders
    robot arms designed for nuclear waste facilities
    computer workstations
    Neptune robot
    Learning Robots Laboratory room
    use of a light stripe rangefinder
    robot arm reassembling wood block configurations using a task oriented vision system.
    Transcript, 1-37 pages, of videotape recording, 2 hours.
  - Supplemental Tape/Set 1: 24 July 1989 (Box 1 of 1)
    At the National Bureau of Standards, with Lubar, Thomas Wheatly, James Albus, and robot "Erica," c. 1989, includes description of robot.
    robot movements
    laboratory. Transcript, none, of videotape recording, 1 hour.
  - Supplemental Tape/Set 2: 20-21 April 1989 (Box 1 of 1)
    At Texas Tech University, with students, faculty, and observers for the "Walking Machine Decathalon," c. 1989, includes the participation of students and robots in events.
    close-ups of robots
    robotics movements
    location of competition.
    Transcript, none, of videotape recording, 8 hours.
  - Video Recordings of Interviews
  - Session 1: 31 March 1989 (Box 1 of 1)
    Total Recording Time: 2 hours, 40 minutes
    Original Masters: 8 Beta videotapes
    Preservation Masters: 8 Motion jpeg 2000 and 8 mpeg digital files
    Dubbing Masters: 3 U-matic videotapes
    Reference Copies: 2 VHS videotapes, 3 Windows Media Video and 3 Real Media digital files
  - Session 2: 14 December 1989 (Box 1 of 1)
    Total Recording Time: 3 hours, 20 minutes
    Original Masters: 10 Beta videotapes
    Preservation Masters: 10 Motion jpeg 2000 and 10 mpeg digital files
    Dubbing Masters: 4 U-matic videotapes
    Reference Copies: 2 VHS videotapes, 4 Windows Media Video and 4 Real Media digital files
  - Session 3: 20 September 1990 (Box 1 of 1)
    Total Recording Time: 3 hours, 40 minutes
    Original Masters: 11 Beta videotapes
    Preservation Masters: 11 Motion jpeg 2000 and 11 mpeg digital files
    Dubbing Masters: 4 U-matic videotapes, (3:40)
  - Session 4: 21 September 1990 (Box 1 of 1)
    Total Time Recording: 2 hours
    Original Masters: 5 Beta videotapes
    Preservation Masters: 5 Motion jpeg 2000 and 5 mpeg digital files
    Dubbing Masters: 2 U-matic videotapes
    Reference Copies: 1 VHS videotape, 2 Windows Media Video and 2 Real Media digital files
  - Supplemental Tape/Set 1: 24 July 1989 (Box 1 of 1)
    Total Recording Time: 1 hour
    Original Masters: 3 U-matic videotapes
    Preservation Masters: 3 Motion jpeg 2000 and 3 mpeg digital files
    Dubbing Masters: 1 U-matic videotape
    Reference Copies: 1 VHS videotape, 1 Windows Media Video and 1 Real Media digital files
  - Supplemental Tape/Set 2: 20-21 April 1989 (Box 1 of 1)
    Total Recording Time: 8 hours
    Original Masters: not available
    Preservation Masters: not available
    Dubbing Masters: not available
    Reference Copies: 4 VHS videotapes